Finding Aid for First Unitarian-Universalist Church Records
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Church Committees and Organizations
  - Women's Alliance (National Alliance of Unitarian and Other Liberal Christian Women)
    - Reports
      - 1895-1910 (Box 11)
      - 1920-1932 (Box 11)
      - 1933-1938 (Box 11)
      - 1939-1942 (Box 11)
      - 1948-1952 (Box 11)
    - Reports (subcommittees) 1933-1955 (Box 11)
    - Directories 1935-1936, 1986-1989, 1991-1995, 1997-2005 (Box 11)
    - Membership rosters
      - 1950s (Box 11)
      - 1963-1967 (Box 11)
    - Minutes (bound)
      - 1891-1897 (Box 12)
      - 1897-1901 (Box 12)
      - 1904-1905 (Box 12)
      - 1907-1910 (Box 12)
      - 1910-1912 (Box 12)
      - 1916-1920 (Box 12)
      - 1920-1935 (Box 12)
      - 1930-1940 (Box 12)
      - 1935-1955 (Box 12)
      - 1940-1950 (Box 12)
    - Minutes
      - 1962-1964 (Box 12)
      - 1965 (Box 12)
      - 1966 (Box 12)
      - 1967-1968 (Box 12)
      - 1969-1971 (Box 12)
      - 1977-1980 (Box 12)
      - 1980s (Box 12)
      - 1990s (Box 12)
      - 2000-2007 (Box 13)
    - Account book 1920-1928 (Box 13)
    - Correspondence 1965-1967 (Box 13)
    - Services and hymns 1927 (Box 13)
    - Words from a Free Pulpit (publication), 1902 (Box 13)
    - Alliance Potpourri (newsletter), 1964-1968 (Box 13)
    - Programming and events
      - 1947-1948, 1953, 1959-1961 (Box 13)
      - 1982-1994, undated (Box 13)
    - Photographs, assorted events 1980s-1990s, 2 folders (Box 13)
    - Junior Alliance
      - Minutes
        - 1908-1911 (bound) (Box 13)
        - 1911-1915 (bound) (Box 13)
      - Flower Committee 1912-1915 (Box 13)
    - Ladies Industrial Circle undated (Box 13)
    - Miscellaneous records 1920, 1922, 1950s undated (Box 13)
  - Other Women's Groups
    The fourth subseries contains administrative records, minutes, and correspondence from other national and Michigan-based women's groups, including the Ladies Union of the First Universalist Church of Detroit and the Clara Barton Sisterhood.
    - Ladies Union of the First Universalist Church of Detroit
      - Constitution, circa 1900 (Box 13)
      - Constitution and membership rosters (bound) 1899-1912 (Box 13)
      - Yearbooks 1912, 1915, 1917, 1919 (Box 13)
      - Annual reports
        - 1897, 1899, 1900 (Box 13)
        - 1901-1902 (Box 13)
        - 1904-1905 (Box 13)
        - 1906-1908 (Box 13)
      - Treasurer's reports 1892-1896 (Box 13)
      - Miscellaneous reports 1895-1905 (Box 13)
      - Minutes
        - 1891-1896 (bound) (Box 13)
        - 1915-1920 (Box 13)
      - Record book 1891-1895 (Box 13)
      - Correspondence and other records 1900, 1901, 1906, 1922, 1924 (Box 13)
      - Book of recipes 1915 (Box 13)
    - The Clara Barton Sisterhood
      - Biographies 1983, 1988 (Box 13)
      - "In sisterhood...the life stories of the Unitarian-Universalist Women's Federation Clara Barton Sisters" (Unitarian-Universalist Women's Federation) 1989 (Box 13)
    - Association of Universalist Women, yearbooks 1945, 1948, 1950 (Box 13)
    - Unitarian-Universalist Women's Federation, newsletters 1983-1984 (Box 13)
    - Women's Guild, minutes and reports 1926-1928 (Box 13)
    - Assorted Michigan-based women's groups, assorted records 1914, 1951 (Box 13)
    - Unspecified women's interest groups, minutes (bound) 1888-1896 (Box 13)
- Church Activities
  The Church Activities series (3.7 linear feet, one oversize box, and one oversize folder) is comprised of two subseries (Religious Education and Church Events).
  - Religious Education
    The first subseries contains reports, financial records, policies and procedures, programs, and newsletters for the church's religious education program (known first as First U-U Sunday School and later as the Second Story Church). The subseries also contains the records of the Religious Education Committee, which consist predominantly of meeting minutes and reports. The bulk of the subseries is composed of curricular and reference materials, which include books and other publications intended primarily for children and adolescents on the topics of religious philosophy and values, spiritual and intellectual development, ethics, and the traditions of other religions. The subseries also contains a number of Christian, Universalist, and Unitarian periodicals and informational pamphlets on the topics of Unitarian-Universalist philosophy and history, religious liberalism, and political and social issues of importance to the church.
    - First U-U Sunday School
      - Reports and other records 1900-1905, 1920-1925, 1939 (Box 14)
      - Financial records 1873-1878 (Box 14)
      - Orders of service 1874, 1883-1885 (Box 14)
      - Library catalogs 1886, 1889, 1893 (Box 14)
    - First U-U Religious Education
      - Policies and procedures undated (Box 14)
      - Teacher's manual 1999 (Box 14)
      - School programs and prospectus 1960s, 1972-1975, 1980-1998, 2006 (Box 14)
      - "Second Story Church," newsletters 1987-1989, 1991 undated (Box 14)
      - Religious education staff, photographs, circa 1990 (Box 14)
    - Religious Education Committee
      - Reports and related documents 1904, 1919, 1938, 1942 undated (Box 14)
      - Reports 1990, 1993-2000 (Box 14)
      - Minutes 1980, 1983, 1989-1992 (Box 14)
      - Correspondence 2003 (Box 14)
      - Religious education news 2003 (Box 14)
    - Curricular/Reference Materials
      - A Catechism for Unitarian-Universalists, by Rev. Dr. Tony Larson (U-U Church of Racine and Kenosha, WI) undated (Box 14)
      - Buddhism 2006 (Box 14)
      - Coming of Age: A Program for 8th Grade Students (U-U Church of Farmington, Farmington Hills, MI) 1994 (Box 14)
      - Coming of Age Program 1992 (Box 14)
      - Coming of Age Program (Prairie Star District) undated (Box 14)
      - Compassion Project 1991 (Box 14)
      - Development in Meanings: A Major Task for Religious Education undated (Box 14)
      - Famous Unitarian-Universalists, biographical materials 1960s-1990s (Box 14)
      - Focus on Values and Goals '73, by Ruth Mendelsohn (UUA) 1973 (Box 14)
      - How Others Worship 1978 (Box 14)
      - Introduction to Unitarianism, by Paul Carnes (Council of Liberal Churches) undated (Box 14)
      - Liberal Religious Education (journal of the Liberal Religious Educator's Association), 1994, 1995 (Box 14)
      - Life Planning Manual 1981 (Box 14)
      - The New Unitarian-Universalist Orientation Program for New Members (UUA) 1989 (Box 14)
      - Odyssey/Four (spiritual enrichment program) (UUA) 1981, 2 folders (Box 14)
      - Owning Your Religious Past: The Haunting Church, by Bonnie H. Stauffacher 1981 (Box 14)
      - Peace and Non-Violence 1995 (Box 14)
      - Peace Child (play) 1988 (Box 14)
      - Peace Experiments, edited by Terry Hermson (Unitarian-Universalist Peace Network) 1984 (Box 14)
      - Self-Discovery: Group Explorations in Life Crises, by Doris Pullen (UUA) 1972 (Box 14)
      - Sexism and Peacemaking undated (Box 14)
      - The Skinner Sermon Award 1984, 1985, 1989, 1990 (Box 14)
      - Thinking the Web: Unitarian-Universalism and Controversial Moral Issues for High School Youth 1997 (Box 15)
      - What is Religion: For Others and for Us 1984 (Box 15)
      - Who was Jesus 1989 (Box 15)
      - Young Adult Ministries (UUA), assorted educational materials 1990s (Box 15)
      - Assorted programmatic materials 1960s-1990s (Box 15)
      - Assorted adult educational programs 1981-1991 (Box 15)
      - Assorted essays and articles on religious philosophy and pedagogy 1960s, 1980s, 1990 undated (Box 15)
      - Assorted sermons (Theodore Parker) 1845, 1858-1859, undated (Box 15)
    - Books
      - A Growing-Up Year: A Program for Eleven to Thirteen Year-Olds, by Margaret K. Gooding, 1988 (Box 15)
      - A Stream of Living Souls: 36 Stories for Home and Worship, by Denise D. Tracy, undated (Box 15)
      - Around the Church, Around the Year: Unitarian-Universalism for Children, by John Evans-Tiller, 1990 (Box 15)
      - Beyond Pink and Blue: Exploring our Stereotypes of Sexuality and Gender, by Tracey Robinson-Harris and Ritch C. Williams, 1994 (Box 15)
      - Life Issues for Teenagers, by Wayne Arnason and Cheryl Markoff-Powers, 1985 (Box 15)
      - On the Path: Spirituality for Youth and Adults, edited by David Marshak, 1989 (Box 15)
      - Philosophy-Making: A Process Guide, by Elizabeth Anastos and David Marshak, 1984 (Box 15)
      - Special Times: Honoring our Jewish and Christian Heritages, by Betty-Jo Middleton, 1994 (Box 15)
      - The Tuckers Growing to Know Themselves, by Katherine S. Wensberg, 1961 (Box 15)
      - The Unitarian-Universalist Kids Book, by Brotman and Marshfield, 1989 (Box 15)
      - Worshipping Together with Questioning Minds, by Sophia Lyon-Fahs, 1965 (Box 15)
    - Pamphlets
      - About Unitarian-Universalism 1906, 1940s-1990s, 3 folders (Box 15)
      - African-American and Hispanic membership 1990s-2000s (Box 15)
      - Church history and development 1950s-1980s (Box 15)
      - Famous Unitarians 1950s-2000s (Box 15)
      - Gender and sexuality 1990s undated (Box 15)
      - Humanism and religious liberalism undated (Box 15)
      - Philosophy and religion 1920s-1980s, 3 folders (Box 15)
      - Political and social issues 1943, 1970s-1990s, 2001 (Box 16)
      - Ralph Waldo Emerson undated (Box 16)
      - Religious education and children 1950s-1990s (Box 16)
      - Religious views 1980s-1990s, undated (Box 16)
      - Unitarianism and Unitarian history
        - 1880-1922 (Box 16)
        - 1924 (Box 16)
        - Undated (Box 16)
      - Views on other religions 1960s-1980s (Box 16)
    - Publications
      - Charles Street Universalist Meeting House, 1953 (Box 16)
      - The Christian Leader, 1944, 1945, 1947, 1948 (Box 16)
      - The Christian Register, 1895, 1900, 1901 (Box 16)
      - Community Pulpit (Community Church of New York), 1982-1987 (Box 16)
      - Detroit Universalist, undated (Box 16)
      - Faith and Freedom, 1952, 1956 (Box 16)
      - Forum, 1955 (Box 16)
      - The Inquirer, 1955 (Box 16)
      - The Midland Unitarian Quarterly, 1954-1955 (Box 16)
      - The Myrtle, 1880 (Box 16)
      - Sermon of the Month (First Unitarian Church of Los Angeles), 1954-1956 (Box 16)
      - The Toledo Unitarian Pulpit, 1982, 1986 (Box 16)
      - The Unitarian, 1955, 1957, 1958 (Box 16)
      - The Universalist Herald, 1982 (Box 16)
      - The Universalist Leader, 1955, 1957, 1958 (Box 16)
      - Voice of Fellowship, 1981-1982 (Box 16)
      - Window on the World, 1983-1984 (Box 16)
      - World, 1993, 2001-2003 (Box 16)
  - Church Events
    The second subseries is predominantly comprised of photographs of church events, which include conventions, fundraisers, trips, cultural and artistic programs, holidays, and social events. The subseries also includes two scrapbooks, which contain newspaper clippings, programs, and photographs of assorted church activities. The subseries also contains a small subset of materials pertaining to the church's political and social engagement, which includes such issues as racial and gender equality and opposition to war.
    - Church events
      - Church anniversaries 1950, 1975, 1991 (Box 16)
      - Commemorative masses and dedications 1916, 1950s, 1975, 1991, 2011 (Box 16)
      - Lay leadership program 1987-1988, undated (Box 16)
      - Lectures 1901, 1907, 1909, 1911 (Box 16)
      - Assorted events programs 1877, 1909, 1910 (Box 16)
    - Photographs of church events
      - 95th anniversary 2011 (Box 16)
      - Annual community convention 2000 (Box 16)
      - Arts and crafts 1968, 1971 undated (Box 16)
      - Auction 1987 (Box 16)
      - Belle Isle picnic 1990s (Box 16)
      - Bulletin board materials 2007-2009 (Box 16)
      - Chicago Children's Choir 1973 (Box 16)
      - Church trips (Italy, Israel) 1982 undated (Box 16)
      - Classroom lessons 1940s, 1968 undated (Box 16)
      - Coffee hours 1959, 1969 undated (Box 16)
      - Dinner in Pullman Hall 1990s (Box 16)
      - Doublets Club campout undated (Box 16)
      - Edwardian Evenings 1979, 1980s (Box 16)
      - Fashion show 1982 (Box 16)
      - German dinner 1993 (Box 16)
      - Golden Jubilee: 50 years of Unitarian-Universalism 1985 (Box 16)
      - "Hall of fame," 1996 (Box 16)
      - Health fair 1991 (Box 17)
      - Holiday events 1980s-1990s (Box 17)
      - Horizons in poetry with Ron Allen 1999-2001 (Box 17)
      - Kwanzaa concert 1992 (Box 17)
      - Membership Sunday 1969, 1996, 2000 (Box 17)
      - Multiple Arts Club events undated (Box 17)
      - Musical events 1980s-1990s (Box 17)
      - Noel Night 1979, 1989, 1999 undated (Box 17)
      - "Out Now" Vietnam War rally 1971 (Box 17)
      - Red Door Players 1979, 1980s (Box 17)
      - Roaring 20's dinner 1982 (Box 17)
      - Rummage sales 1980s-1999 (Box 17)
      - Speakers undated (Box 17)
      - Thanksgiving 1980s (Box 17)
      - Upland Hills farm trip undated (Box 17)
      - Unitarian anniversary lecture undated (Box 17)
      - Valentine's film party 1986 (Box 17)
      - Victorian tea 1982 (Box 17)
      - Visitors from Minsk 1986 (Box 17)
      - Waterloo, MI 1980s-1990s (Box 17)
      - Miscellaneous church activities 1970s-2004, 4 folders (Box 17)
      - Dedication banquet of the First Universalist Church 1916 (Folder 1)
      - Second annual chapter convention of the Unitarian Laymen's League 1922 (Folder 1)
    - Scrapbooks
      - Assorted church activities (newspaper clippings, orders of service, events programs) 1944-1956 (Box 23)
      - Assorted events (photographs and newspaper clippings) 1982-1983 (Box 23)
    - Social and political issues
      - Racism and racial justice 1996 (Box 17)
      - Sexual abuse materials undated (Box 17)
      - Social justice empowerment program 1991 (Box 17)
      - War/peace/nuclear disarmament 1980s undated (Box 17)
      - Activities pertaining to miscellaneous social issues 1917, 1967, 1976, 2003 (Box 17)
- Newsletters and Orders of Service
  The Newsletters and Orders of Service series (5.3 linear feet) consists of church newsletters and orders of service (weekly worship programs), all of which are organized by year. The series contains newsletters from the years 1882-1903, 1926-1936, 1941-1943, 1954-1956, and 1958-2010, and orders of service from the years 1898-1916, 1932-1958, and 1969-2010.
  - Newsletters (bound)
    - 1882-1883 (Box 17)
    - 1893-1896 (Box 17)
    - 1896-1899 (Box 17)
    - 1899-1903 (Box 17)
  - 1882, 1885 newsletters (Box 18)
  - 1898-1904 orders of service (Box 18)
  - 1905 orders of service (Box 18)
  - 1906 orders of service (Box 18)
  - 1907 orders of service (Box 18)
  - 1908-1916 orders of service (Box 18)
  - 1926-1931 newsletters (Box 18)
  - 1932-1936 newsletters and orders of service (Box 18)
  - 1937-1939 orders of service (Box 18)
  - 1941-1942 newsletters and orders of service (Box 18)
  - 1943 newsletters and orders of service (Box 18)
  - 1944 orders of service, 2 folders (Box 18)
  - 1945 orders of service, 2 folders (Box 18)
  - 1946 orders of service, 2 folders (Box 18)
  - 1947 orders of service, 2 folders (Box 18)
  - 1948 orders of service, 2 folders (Box 18)
  - 1949 orders of service, 2 folders (Box 18)
  - 1950 orders of service, 5 folders (Box 18)
  - 1951 orders of service, 5 folders (Box 18)
  - 1952 orders of service, 3 folders (Box 18)
  - 1953 orders of service, 3 folders (Box 18)
  - The Liberal Log (newsletter), 1954-1956 (Box 18)
  - 1954 orders of service, 3 folders (Box 18)
  - 1955 orders of service, 3 folders (Box 18)
  - 1956 orders of service, 2 folders (Box 18)
  - 1957 orders of service, 2 folders (Box 18)
  - 1958 newsletters and orders of service, 2 folders (Box 18)
  - 1959 newsletters, 2 folders (Box 19)
  - 1960 newsletters (Church of our Father) (Box 19)
  - 1960 newsletters (First Unitarian-Universalist Church of Detroit) (Box 19)
  - 1961 newsletters, 2 folders (Box 19)
  - 1962 newsletters, 2 folders (Box 19)
  - 1963 newsletters, 2 folders (Box 19)
  - 1964 newsletters, 2 folders (Box 19)
  - 1965 newsletters, 2 folders (Box 19)
  - 1966 newsletters, 2 folders (Box 19)
  - 1967 newsletters, 2 folders (Box 19)
  - 1968 newsletters, 2 folders (Box 19)
  - 1969 newsletters and orders of service (Box 19)
  - 1970 newsletters and orders of service (Box 19)
  - 1971 newsletters and orders of service (Box 19)
  - 1972 newsletters (Box 19)
  - 1973 newsletters and orders of service (Box 19)
  - 1974 newsletters and orders of service (Box 19)
  - 1975 newsletters and orders of service (Box 19)
  - 1976 newsletters and orders of service (Box 19)
  - 1977 newsletters and orders of service (Box 19)
  - 1978 newsletters and orders of service (Box 19)
  - 1979 newsletters and orders of service (Box 20)
  - 1980 newsletters and orders of service (Box 20)
  - 1981 newsletters and orders of service (Box 20)
  - 1982 newsletters and orders of service (Box 20)
  - 1983 newsletters and orders of service (Box 20)
  - 1984 newsletters and orders of service, 2 folders (Box 20)
  - 1985 newsletters and orders of service, 2 folders (Box 20)
  - 1986 newsletters and orders of service (Box 20)
  - 1987 newsletters and orders of service (Box 20)
  - 1988 newsletters and orders of service (Box 20)
  - 1989 newsletters and orders of service (Box 20)
  - 1990 newsletters and orders of service (Box 20)
  - 1991 newsletters and orders of service (Box 21)
  - 1992 orders of service (Box 21)
  - 1992 newsletters (Box 21)
  - 1993 orders of service (Box 21)
  - 1993 newsletters (Box 21)
  - 1994 orders of service (Box 21)
  - 1994 newsletters (Box 21)
  - 1995 orders of service (Box 21)
  - 1995 newsletters (Box 21)
  - 1996 orders of service (Box 21)
  - 1996 newsletters (Box 21)
  - 1997 orders of service (Box 21)
  - 1997 newsletters (Box 21)
  - 1998 orders of service (Box 21)
  - 1998 newsletters (Box 21)
  - 1999 orders of service (Box 21)
  - 1999 newsletters (Box 21)
  - 2000 orders of service (Box 21)
  - 2000 newsletters (Box 21)
  - 2001 orders of service (Box 22)
  - 2001 newsletters (Box 22)
  - 2002 orders of service (Box 22)
  - 2002 newsletters (Box 22)
  - 2003 orders of service (Box 22)
  - 2003 newsletters (Box 22)
  - 2004 orders of service (Box 22)
  - 2004 newsletters (Box 22)
  - 2005 orders of service (Box 22)
  - 2005 newsletters (Box 22)
  - 2006 orders of service (Box 22)
  - 2006 newsletters (Box 22)
  - 2007 orders of service (Box 22)
  - 2007 newsletters (Box 22)
  - 2008 orders of service (Box 22)
  - 2008 newsletters (Box 22)
  - 2009 orders of service (Box 22)
  - 2009 newsletters (Box 22)
  - 2010 orders of service (Box 22)
  - 2010 newsletters (Box 22)
  - Undated, orders of service (Box 22)